<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter" part="I">
            <pb/>
            <head>3. SIMULATING CLIMATIC CHANGE</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p n="1">In order to project the impact of human perturbations on the climate system,
                  it is necessary to calculate the effects of all the key processes operating in the
                  climate system. These processes can be represented in mathematical terms, but the
                  complexity of the system means that the calculations can only be performed in
                  practice using a computer. The mathematical formulation is therefore implemented
                  in a computer program, which we refer to as a "model". If the model includes
                  enough of the components of the climate system to be useful for simulating the
                  climate, it is commonly called a "climate model".</p>
               <p n="2">A climate model which explicitly included all our current understanding of
                  the climate system would be too complex to run on any existing computer. For
                  practical purposes, some compromises have to be made. The basic question is: in
                  how much detail should the components and processes of the climate system be
                  represented? If the representation is simplified, fewer calculations are needed
                  and the model can be run faster or on a less powerful computer.</p>
               <p n="3">The most detailed model of a particular process is one which is based on
                  fundamental physical principles which we believe to be invariant. Such a model
                  would be applicable to any climate. In order to represent the process in a way
                  which can be used in a climate model, additional, simplifying assumptions have to
                  be introduced. In some cases, empirically-derived relationships are included. When
                  this is necessary, the range of the validity of the model will inevitably become
                  more limited. As far as possible, climate models make use of basic physical
                  principles or of simplifications which introduce minimal uncertainty. This is
                  necessary because the conditions of a changed climate may be quite different from
                  current conditions, so relationships derived empirically or statistically for the
                  current climate will not necessarily hold <name>(SAR WGI: Section 1.6)</name>.</p>
               <p n="4">In the most complex climate models, physical quantities which vary
                  continuously in three dimensions are represented by their values at a finite
                  number of points arranged in a threedimensional grid. This is clearly necessary
                  because we can do only a finite number of calculations. The spacing between the
                  points of the grid is the "spatial resolution". The finer the resolution, the
                  larger the number of points, and the more calculations there are to be done.
                  Hence, the resolution is limited by the computing resources available. The typical
                  resolution that can be used in a climate model is hundreds of kilometres in the
                  horizontal. Many important elements of the climate system (e.g., clouds, land
                  surface variations) have scales much smaller than this. Detailed models at high
                  resolution are available for such processes by themselves, but these are
                  computationally too expensive to be included in a climate model. Instead, the
                  climate model has to represent the effect of these sub-grid scale processes on the
                  climate system at its coarse grid scale. A formulation of the effect of a
                  small-scale process on the large-scale is called a "parametrization" <name>(SAR
                     WGI: Section 1.6.1)</name>. All climate models use parametrization to some
                  extent.</p>
               <p n="5">Another kind of simplification used in climate models is to average over a
                  spatial dimension. Thus, instead of a three-dimensional longitude-latitude-height
                  grid, one might use a two-dimensional latitude-height grid, with each point being
                  an average over all longitudes at that latitude and height. When the
                  dimensionality is reduced, more processes have to be parametrized.</p>
               <p n="6">In the following sub-sections, we briefly outline the major types of models
                  that have been developed for each of the major steps involved in simulating the
                  climate and sea level response to anthropogenic emissions. This provides a context
                  for the specific simple climate models that have been used by the IPCC and which
                  are described in Section 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection" part="I" n="3.1">
               <head>3.1 A Hierarchy of Atmosphere and Ocean Climate Models</head>
               <p n="7">Some of the main types of models for the atmospheric and oceanic components
                  of the climate system are as follows:</p>
               <p n="8">One-dimensional radiative-convective atmospheric models. These models are
                  globally (horizontally) averaged but contain many layers within the atmosphere.
                  They treat processes related to the transfer of solar and infrared radiation
                  within the atmosphere in considerable detail, and are particularly useful for
                  computing the radiative forcing associated with changes in the atmosphere's
                  composition. The change in atmospheric water vapour amount as climate changes must
                  be prescribed (based on observations), but the impact on radiation associated with
                  a given change in water vapour can be accurately computed. Radiative-convective
                  models thus provide one means for determining one of the key feedbacks which are
                  important to climate sensitivity through a combination of observations and
                  wellestablished physical processes.</p>
               <p n="9">One-dimensional upwelling-diffusion ocean models. The atmosphere is treated
                  as a single well-mixed box that exchanges heat with the underlying ocean and land
                  surface. The absorption of solar radiation by the atmosphere and surface depends
                  on the specified surface reflectivity and atmospheric transmissivity and
                  reflectivity. The emission of infrared radiation to space is a linearly increasing
                  function of atmospheric temperature in this model, with the constant of
                  proportionality serving as the infrared radiative damping. The ocean is treated as
                  a one-dimensional column which represents a horizontal average over the real
                  ocean, excluding the limited regions where deep water forms and sinks to the ocean
                  bottom, which are treated separately. Figure 2 illustrates this model. The sinking
                  in polar regions is represented by the pipe to the side of the column. This
                  sinking and the compensating upwelling within the column represent the global
                  scale thermohaline circulation. This model is used primarily to study the role of
                  the oceans in the surface temperature response to changes in radiative
                  forcing.</p>
            </div>

            <pb/>
            <div type="subsection" part="F" n="3.1">
               <label>16 An Introduction to Simple Climate Models used in the IPCC Second Assessment
                  Report </label>
               <figure>
                  <desc>Figure 2. Illustration of the upwelling-diffusion climate model, consisting
                     of a single atmospheric box, a surface layer representing both land and the
                     ocean mixed-layer, and a deep ocean. Solar and infrared radiative transfers,
                     air-sea heat exchange, and deep ocean mixing by diffusion and thermohaline
                     overturning are all represented in this model and are indicated in the figure
                        <name>(based on Harvey and Schneider, (1985)</name>).</desc>
               </figure>
               <p n="10">One-dimensional energy balance models. In these models, the only dimension
                  that is represented is the variation with latitude; the atmosphere is averaged
                  vertically and in the east-west direction, and is often combined with the surface
                  to form a single layer. The multiple processes of north-south heat transport by
                  the atmosphere and oceans are usually represented as diffusion, while infrared
                  emission to space is represented in the same way as in the upwelling-diffusion
                  model. These models have provided a number of useful insights concerning the
                  interaction of horizontal heat transport feedbacks and high latitude feedbacks
                  involving ice and snow.</p>
               <p n="10">Two-dimensional atmosphere and ocean models. Several different
                  two-dimensional (latitude-height or latitude-depth) models of the atmosphere and
                  oceans have been developed <eg>(e.g., <name>Peng and Arking (1982)</name>, for the
                     atmosphere; <name>Wright and Stocker (1991)</name>, for the ocean)</eg>. The
                  two-dimensional models permit a more physically based computation of horizontal
                  heat transport than in one-dimensional energy balance models. In some
                  twodimensional ocean models <eg>(e.g., <name>Wright and Stocker, 1991</name>)</eg>
                  the intensity of the thermohaline overturning is determined by the model itself,
                  while in others <eg>(e.g., <name>de Wolde, et al., 1995</name>)</eg> it is
                  prescribed, as in the one-dimensional upwelling-diffusion model. The
                  one-dimensional energy balance atmosphere-surface climate model has also been
                  coupled to a two-dimensional ocean model (<name>Harvey, 1992</name>; <name>de
                     Wolde, et al., 1995</name>, and <name>Bintanja, 1995</name>). It is relatively
                  easy to run separate two-dimensional ocean models for each of the Atlantic,
                  Pacific, and Indian Ocean basins, with a connection at their southern boundaries
                  (representing the Antarctic Ocean) and interaction with a single, zonally-averaged
                  atmosphere.</p>
               <p n="11">Three-dimensional atmosphere and ocean general circulation models. The most
                  complex atmosphere and ocean models are the three-dimensional AGCMs and ocean
                  general circulation models (OGCMs), both of which are extensively reviewed in the
                  SAR WGI (Chapter 5). These models divide the atmosphere or ocean into a horizontal
                  grid with a typical resolution of 2-4 ยบ latitude by 2-4 ยบ longitude in
                  the latest models, and typically 10 to 20 layers in the vertical. They directly
                  simulate winds, ocean currents, and many other variables and processes
                  characterizing the atmosphere and oceans. Both AGCMs and OGCMs have been used
                  extensively in a stand-alone mode, with prescribed ocean surface temperatures and
                  sea ice in the case of AGCMs and with prescribed surface temperatures and
                  salinities, or the corresponding heat and freshwater fluxes, in the case of OGCMs.
                  An AOGCM consists of an AGCM coupled to an OGCM, with information about the state
                  of the atmosphere and ocean adjacent to, or at the sea surface, used to compute
                  exchanges of heat, moisture and momentum between the two components.</p>
               <p n="12">AOGCMs compute radiative transfer through the atmosphere (explicitly
                  modelling clouds, water vapour and other atmospheric components), snow and sea
                  ice, surface fluxes, transport of heat and water by the atmosphere and ocean, as
                  well as the uptake of heat by the oceans (which delays and modifies the initial
                  surface temperature response but contributes to sea level rise through expansion
                  of ocean water as it warms). Thus, coupled AOGCMs explicitly compute the fast
                  feedback processes, whose interactive effect determines climate sensitivity.
                  Because of computational constraints, however, the majority of these processes are
                  parametrized to some extent (<ref>see SAR WGI, Sections 4.2 and 4.3</ref>,
                  concerning processes in atmospheric and oceanic GCMs, respectively). More detailed
                  representations are either not practical or have not been developed for use in a
                  global model. Some parametrizations inevitably include constants which have been
                  tuned to observations of the current climate. AOGCMs attempt to explicitly
                  represent a large number of processes, while simpler models represent these
                  processes by a small number of adjustable parameters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection" part="I" n="3.2">
               <head>3.2 Models of the Carbon Cycle</head>
               <p n="13" part="I">The carbon cycle is an integral part of the climate system, and
                  governs the build-up of atmospheric CO2 in response to human emissions. The key
                  processes that need to be accurately simulated are photosynthesis and respiration
                  on land, and the net exchange of CO2 between the ocean and atmosphere. Because</p>
            </div>

            <pb/>
            <div type="subsection" n="3.2" part="F" >
               <label>An Introduction to Simple Climate Models used in the IPCC Second Assessment
                  Report 17</label>
               <p n="13" part="F">CO2 is chemically inert in the atmosphere and of rather uniform
                  concentration, natural changes in atmospheric CO2 concentration depend only on the
                  global sum of the photosynthesis, respiration, and air-sea flows. However, each of
                  these flows exhibits substantial variation in time and space and depends on a
                  number of poorly understood sub-processes <ref>(SAR WGI: Chapters 9 and 10;</ref>
                  <ref>IPCC WGII, 19963: Chapter A)</ref>. For example, long-term changes in both
                  the photosynthetic and respiration flows of carbon between the terrestrial
                  biosphere and the atmosphere are modulated by processes involving soil nutrients
                  and micro-organisms, while the air-sea flow is modulated by a number of processes
                  that affect the concentration of CO2 in surface water. These include vertical
                  mixing of total dissolved carbon and the net sinking of particulate organic matter
                  and carbonate material into the deep ocean, which is driven in part by surface
                  biological productivity. The latter, in turn, will be influenced by vertical
                  mixing of nutrients and changes in temperature. Changes in ocean circulation will,
                  thus, influence the air-sea exchange of CO2 by altering the exchange of total
                  dissolved carbon between the surface layer and deep ocean, and by altering
                  biological productivity by changing the flow of nutrients from the deep ocean to
                  surface layer.</p>
               <p n="14">The one-dimensional upwelling-diffusion model can be used as the oceanic
                  part of the carbon cycle (<name>Hoffert, et al., 1981</name>; <name>Piehler and
                     Bach, 1992</name>). The global mean atmosphere-ocean exchange of CO2, the
                  vertical mixing of total dissolved carbon by thermohaline overturning and
                  diffusion, and the sinking of particulate material produced by biological activity
                  can all be represented in this model. A two-dimensional ocean model has been used
                  as the oceanic component of the global carbon cycle (<name>Stocker, et al.,
                     1994</name>). Finally, OGCMs can be used as the oceanic component of the global
                  carbon cycle, in which the model-computed ocean currents and other mixing
                  processes are used, in combination with simple representations of biological
                  processes and air-sea exchange (e.g., <name>Bacastow and Maier-Reimer,
                  1990</name>; <name>Najjar, et al., 1992</name>). At the time of the SAR, CO2
                  uptake calculations using three-dimensional models had been published only for
                  standalone OGCMs, in which the circulation field and surface temperatures were
                  fixed. In a coupled simulation, changes in both of these variables, in response to
                  increasing greenhouse gas concentrations, would alter the subsequent uptake of CO2
                  to some extent (<ref>see SAR WGI: Chapter 10</ref>). </p>
               <p n="15">A variety of globally aggregated box models of the terrestrial biosphere
                  have also been developed and used, in conjunction with simple models of the
                  oceanic part of the carbon cycle, to project future atmospheric CO2 concentration.
                  The commonly used global box models are quantitatively compared in Harvey (1989).
                  Because the terrestrial biosphere is globally aggregated in the SCMs used in the
                  SAR WGI, it is not possible to simulate separate responses in different latitude
                  zones (e.g., net release of carbon through temperature effects at high latitudes,
                  net uptake of carbon in the tropics due to CO2 fertilization), as obtained in
                  regionally resolved models (van Minnen, et al., 1996). Rather, only a global mean
                  response is simulated. Since regional responses vary non-linearly with temperature
                  and atmospheric CO2 concentration, the use of globally aggregated models
                  undoubtedly introduces errors. </p>
               <p n="16">The role of the terrestrial biosphere in global climatic change has been
                  simulated using relatively simple models of vegetation on a global grid with a
                  resolution as fine as 0.5 ยบ latitude x 0.5 ยบ longitude (SAR WGI:
                  Section 9.4). Such grid-point models simulate the distribution of potential rather
                  than actual vegetation; to simulate the latter requires taking into account human
                  disturbances and soil properties These models have been used to evaluate the
                  impact on net ecosystem productivity of higher atmospheric CO2 (which tends to
                  stimulate photosynthesis and improve the efficiency of water use by plants)4 and
                  warmer temperatures (which can increase or decrease photosynthesis and increase
                  decay processes). These models distinguish, as a minimum, standing biomass from
                  soil organic matter. The more sophisticated varieties track the flows of both
                  carbon and nitrogen (taken to be the limiting nutrient), and include feedbacks
                  between nitrogen and the rates of both photosynthesis and decay of soil carbon
                  (<eg>e.g., <name>Rastetter</name>, et al., 1991, 1992; <name>Melillo</name>, et al., 1993</eg>). </p>
               <p n="17">Grid point models of the terrestrial biosphere have been used to assess the
                  effect on the net biosphere-atmosphere CO2 flux of hypothetical (or GCM-generated)
                  changes in temperature and/or atmospheric CO2 concentration, but generally without
                  allowing for shifts in the ecosystem type at a given grid point as climate
                  changes. More advanced ecosystem models are being developed and tested that link
                  biome models (which predict changing ecosystem types) with ecophysiological models
                  (which predict carbon fluxes) (SAR WGI: Section 9.4). Simulations with these and
                  earlier models demonstrate the potential importance of feedbacks involving the
                  nutrient cycle and indicate the potential magnitude of climateinduced changes in
                  terrestrial biosphere-atmosphere CO2 fluxes. However, individual models still
                  differ considerably in their responses (VEMAP Members, 1995). As with models of
                  the oceanic part of the carbon cycle, such simulations have yet to be carried out
                  interactively with coupled AOGCMs. These models also have not yet been combined
                  with ocean carbon uptake OGCMs.</p>
               <p n="18">Rather detailed models of the marine biosphere, involving a number of
                  species and interactions, have also been developed and applied to specific sites
                  or regions (e.g., Gregg and Walsh, 1992; Sarmiento, et al., 1993; Antoine and
                  Morel, 1995). </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection" part="I" n="3.3">
               <head>3.3 Models of Atmospheric Chemistry and Aerosols </head>
               <p n="19" part="I">Atmospheric chemistry is central to the distribution and amount of
                  ozone in the atmosphere because chemical reactions are</p>
               <note>3 Hereafter referred to as SAR WGII. 4 The stimulatory effect of higher
                  atmospheric CO2 concentration on photosynthesis is referred to as CO2
                  "fertilization", and is discussed further in the accompanying box overleaf.</note>
            </div>
            <pb />
            <div>
            <label>18 An Introduction to Simple Climate Models used in the IPCC Second Assessment
               Report</label>
               <label><hi>Ecosystem responses to changes in atmospheric CO2 concentration and
                     climate</hi></label>
               <p n="20"><hi>Plants in terrestrial ecosystems occupy a central role in the
                     terrestrial carbon cycle, as they take in atmospheric CO2 during photosynthesis
                     and store carbon as biomass. Photosynthetic rates are influenced by plant type,
                     ambient CO2 concentrations and temperature, and are often constrained by
                     nutrients and moisture availability. Higher ambient CO2 levels could enhance
                     plant growth through the CO2-fertilization effect and through an increase in
                     water use efficiency. The response of plants to higher atmospheric CO2
                     concentrations depends, in part, on the particular photosynthetic pathway used
                     (i.e., whether the plants are C3 or C4 -- see SAR WGI: Section 9.2). This
                     introduces significant regional differences in the response of plants to higher
                     CO2. Climatic change further influences plant growth through several pathways.
                     Warmer temperature can either increase or decrease the rate of photosynthesis
                     but will tend to increase the rates of plant respiration, which returns carbon
                     to the atmosphere. The decay of dead biomass (predominantly in soils) also
                     releases CO2 to the atmosphere; such soil respiration is a function of soil
                     type, soil temperature, moisture and nutrient availability. Thus, changes in
                     ambient CO2 concentrations and climate influence ecosystem productivity in a
                     highly non-linear and complex fashion. These ecophysiological processes are
                     discussed in detail in the SAR WGI (Chapter 9) and SAR WGII (Chapter
                  A).</hi></p>
               <p n="21"><hi>Additional changes in ecosystem productivity are caused by changes in
                     land-use practices, nitrogen fertilization (both fertilizer applications and
                     nitrogen deposition through air pollution), and irrigation. However, most SCMs
                     generally only consider deforestation, the most obvious land-use change, which
                     has led to large and immediate changes in global carbon storage.</hi></p>
               <p n="22"><hi>The relationships used in SCMs to compute the response of the
                     terrestrial biosphere to changes in atmospheric CO2 concentrations and climate
                     emphasise mainly enhanced plant growth under changed conditions. The
                     parametrizations used are largely based on short-term glasshouse experiments
                     with responsive plant species under ideal conditions, and do not consider the
                     complex non-linear and interactive effects, systemic feedbacks, and changes in
                     land-use. Simulations with such models suggest that the biosphere will increase
                     its carbon uptake under future conditions. In real ecosystems, the response
                     could be quite different. The complexity and heterogeneity of terrestrial
                     ecosystems and their responses thus make it difficult and dangerous to
                     extrapolate from current conditions far into the future.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection" part="F" n="3.3">
               <p part="F" n="19">responsible for both the production and removal of ozone (O3). The
                  dominant chemical reactions and sensitivities are significantly different for the
                  stratosphere and troposphere. These processes can only be adequately modelled with
                  three-dimensional atmospheric models (in the case of the troposphere) or with
                  two-dimensional (latitude-height) models (in the case of the stratosphere).
                  Atmospheric chemistry is also critical to the removal of methane (CH4) from the
                  atmosphere and, to a lesser extent, all other greenhouse gases except water vapour
                  (H2O) and CO2. In the case of CH4, a change in its concentration affects its own
                  removal rate and, hence, subsequent concentration changes. An accurate simulation
                  of changes in the removal rate of CH4 requires specification of the concurrent
                  concentrations of other reactive species, in particular nitrogen oxides (NOx),
                  carbon monoxide (CO) and the volatile organic compounds (VOCs); and use of a model
                  with latitudinal and vertical resolution. However, simple globally averaged models
                  of chemistry-climate interactions have been developed. These models treat the
                  global CH4-CO-OH cycle in a manner which takes into account the effects of the
                  heterogeneity of the chemical and transport processes, and provide estimates of
                  future global or hemispheric mean changes in the chemistry of the Earth's
                  atmosphere. Some of the models also simulate halocarbon concentrations and the
                  resulting atmospheric chlorine concentration, as well as radiative effects due to
                  halocarbons (Prather, et al., 1992). An even simpler approach is to treat the
                  atmosphere as a single well-mixed box, but to account for the effects of
                  atmospheric chemistry by making the CH4 lifetime depend on CH4 concentration in a
                  way that roughly mimics the behaviour of the above-mentioned globally averaged
                  models or of models with explicit spatial resolution.</p>
               <p n="20">Atmospheric chemistry is also central to the distribution and radiative
                  properties of aerosols, although chemistry is only part of what is required in
                  order to simulate the effects of aerosols on climate. The key processes that need
                  to be represented are the emissions of aerosols or aerosol precursors; atmospheric
                  transport, mixing, and chemical and physical transformation; and removal processes
                  (dry deposition, rain out and wash out). Since part of the effect of aerosols on
                  climate arises because they serve as cloud condensation nuclei (leading to rain
                  out), it is important to be able to represent the relationship between changes in
                  the aerosol mass input to the atmosphere and, ultimately, the radiative properties
                  of clouds. Establishing the link between aerosol emissions and cloud properties,
                  however, involves several poorly understood steps and is highly uncertain.</p>
               <p n="21">Atmospheric O3 and CH4 chemistry is being incorporated into AGCMs for
                  climate simulation purposes. Geographicallydistributed sulphur aerosol emissions
                  have been used as the input to AGCMs and, in combination with representations of
                  aerosol chemical and physical processes, have been used to compute the
                  geographical distribution of sulphur aerosol mass </p>

            </div>
            <pb/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
